Frank Maxwell Andrews Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Frank Maxwell Andrews Papers 1920-1943 (bulk 1935-1942)
MSS11015
Andrews, Frank Maxwell, 1884-1943
5,500 items 19 containers 8 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Air force officer. Correspondence, memoranda, speeches, articles, military service and flight records, reports, financial records, and newspaper clippings relating chiefly to Andrews's career in the military and the organization and administration of the air arm of the War Department and operations of the Caribbean Defense Command at the beginning of World War II.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Andrews, Frank Maxwell, 1884-1943.; Arnold, Henry Harley, 1886-1950--Correspondence.; Bell, Lawrence Dale, 1894-1956--Correspondence.; Brant, Gerald C.--Correspondence.; Brett, George H. (George Howard), 1886-1963--Correspondence.; Chaney, James Eugene, 1885-1967--Correspondence.; Craig, Malin, 1875-1945--Correspondence.; De Seversky, Alexander P. (Alexander Procofieff), 1894-1974--Correspondence.; Fleet, Reuben Hollis, 1887-1975--Correspondence.; Foulois, Benjamin Delahauf, 1879-1967--Correspondence.; Johnson, Louis Arthur, 1891-1966--Correspondence.; Kenney, George C. (George Churchill), 1889-1977--Correspondence.; Knerr, Hugh Johnston, 1887-1971--Correspondence.; Lackland, Frank Dorwin, 1884-1943--Correspondence.; Lane, Arthur Bliss, 1894-1956--Correspondence.; Long, Boaz Walton, 1876-1962--Correspondence.; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959--Correspondence.; McNair, Lesley James, 1883-1944--Correspondence.; Pratt, H. C. (Henry Conger), 1882-1966--Correspondence.; Robins, Augustine Warner--Correspondence.; Spaatz, Carl, 1891-1974--Correspondence.; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950--Correspondence.; Talbot, Ralph, 1897-1918--Correspondence.; Weaver, Walter Reed, 1885-1944--Correspondence.; Westover, Oscar, 1883-1938--Correspondence.; Woodring, Harry Hines, 1887-1967--Correspondence.; Wright, Burdette S.--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Army --History--World War, 1939-1945.; United States. Army. Air Corps.; United States. Army. Air Service.; United States. Army. Caribbean Defense Command.; United States. War Department.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Caribbean Area.
Occupations
Air Force officers.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Frank Maxwell Andrews, air force officer, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Jeanette A. Andrews, in 1949.
Additional Guides
The Frank Maxwell Andrews Papers are described in the Library's Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions, vol. 7, no. 3 (May 1950), pp. 28-29 and further described in in vol. 7, no. 4 (August 1950), pp. 37-40.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Frank Maxwell Andrews are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1884, Feb. 3 Born, Nashville, Tenn.
1906 Graduated, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y. and commissioned a second lieutenant, cavalry
1906-1917 Served with the cavalry in the Philippines, Hawaii, and the continental United States
1914 Married Jeannette Allen
1917 Assigned to the Aviation Division of the Signal Corp
1920-1923 Served with Allied occupation forces in Germany
1923-1935 Commanded various Air Corp stations and units
1935-39 Commanded Air Force, General Headquarters
1940-41 Promoted successively to major and lieutenant general and commanded the Caribbean Air Force and the Caribbean Defense Command
1942 Commanded United States Army Forces, Middle East
1943 Commanding general, European Theater of Operations, United States Army
1943, May 3 Died, Iceland, in an airplane crash
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Frank Maxwell Andrews (1884-1943) span the years 1920-1943, with the bulk of the material from 1935 to 1942. The collection consists of family correspondence, general correspondence, and copies of official correspondence; financial records; reports and memoranda; manuscript and near-print copies of speeches and articles; memorabilia; newspaper clippings; a few other printed items; and additional material, mostly correspondence. Except for Andrews’s military service record (201 File) and flight record, which begin in 1920 and 1921 respectively, there are no materials dated before 1924. There are almost no papers dated after November 1942 when Andrews left the Caribbean Defense Command for the Middle East at Cairo.
The main subjects in the collection are the organization and administration of the air arm of the War Department and the operation of the Caribbean Defense Command as World War II threatened and broke over the western hemisphere.
Andrews's efforts to prepare an effective and modern air force in the late 1930s is recorded in correspondence, memoranda, and reports. Notable are the files of Andrews's correspondence as commander of the General Headquarters, Air Force, Langley Field, with successive chiefs of the Air Corps, Generals Benjamin Delahauf Foulois, Oscar Westover, and Henry Harley Arnold. Correspondence with Secretaries of War Harry Hines Woodring and Henry L. Stimson, Assistant Secretary Louis Arthur Johnson, and General Malin Craig, chief of staff from 1935 to 1939, reflect the views of the War Department concerning air force policy as well as within the air arm itself. From June 1939 until November 1940, Andrews was designated by General George C. Marshall as assistant chief of staff, G-3 (training and operations) of the War Department, the first instance of the appointment of an air officer to a staff position of overall responsibilities within the army. When war began in Europe, Andrews was sent to Panama as chief of the Caribbean Defense Command in charge of all military forces in that area. Except for a few items concerning his death, the papers end at the termination of this assignment.
Other correspondents in the papers include George H. Brett, Gerald C. Brant, Lawrence Dale Bell, James Eugene Chaney, Ruben H. Fleet, Hugh J. Knerr, George C. Kenney, Frank Dorwin Lachland, Boaz Walton Long, Arthur Bliss Lane, Leslie James McNair, Henry Conger Pratt, Augustine Warner Robins, Alexander P. De Seversky, Carl Spaatz, Ralph Talbot, Jr., Burdett S. Wright, Oscar Westover, and Walter Reed Weaver.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eight series:
General Correspondence and Other Papers, 1924-1943
Family Correspondence, 1924-1942
Official Papers, 1920-1943
Financial Papers, 1929-1942
Speeches and Articles File, 1925-1942
Miscellany, 1929-1943
Printed Matter, 1930-1943
Addition, 1930-1942
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78011015
Container List
- General Correspondence and Other Papers, 1924-1943 (Box 1-7)
  Letters sent and received with a few copies of official documents.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - "A-B" miscellaneous, 1924-1942, (10 folders) (Box 1)
  - Craig, Malin, 1935-1939 (Box 2)
  - "C" miscellaneous, 1929-1942, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Daedalians, Order of, 1936-1942 (Box 2)
  - "D-F" miscellaneous, 1930-1942, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - "G-J" miscellaneous, 1929-1942, (9 folders) (Box 4)
  - "K-M" miscellaneous, 1929-1942, (12 folders) (Box 5)
  - "M-S" miscellaneous, 1929-1942, (10 folders) (Box 6)
  - "S-V" miscellaneous, 1930-1942 (Box 7)
  - Westover, Oscar, 1935-1938 (Box 7)
  - "W-Z" miscellaneous, 1929-1943, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Unidentified, 1942-1943 (Box 7)
- Family Correspondence, 1924-1942 (Box 8)
  Letters sent and received with a few genealogical and biographical notes scattered throughout.
  In rough chronological order.
  - 1924-1942, (2 folders) (Box 8)
- Official Papers, 1920-1943 (Box 9-12)
  Correspondence, reports, orders, memoranda, bulletins, personnel and flight records, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
  - Adjutant general, 1935-1942 (Box 9)
  - Air Defense Command, 1941 (Box 9)
  - Airplanes, 1938-1940 (Box 9)
  - Caribbean Defense Command, 1941 (Box 9)
  - General Headquarters, air force (Box 9)
    - Directives, 1930-1937 (Box 9)
    - General orders, 1935-1941 (Box 9)
    - Bulletins, 1935-1937 (Box 9)
    - Data for final report, 1938 (Box 9)
    - Organizations and operations, 1935-1938, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Five-year airplane replacement program, 1937 (Box 10)
    - G-2 (intelligence) bulletins, 1938-1939 (Box 10)
    - Numbered memoranda, 1935-1939, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Office memoranda, 1935-1938 (Box 10)
    - Staff memoranda, 1935-1937 (Box 10)
    - Staff résumé, 1936-1939 (Box 10)
  - Germany, 1937 (Box 10)
  - Italian flight, visit of Italo Baldo to the World's Fair, Chicago, Il., 1933-1934 (Box 11)
  - National defense, 1933-1942 (Box 11)
  - Record flights, 1935-1936 (Box 11)
  - Secretary of war, 1938-1942 (Box 11)
  - Assistant secretary of war, 1937-1942 (Box 11)
  - Visiting dignitaries, 1942 (Box 11)
  - War Department, General Staff, 1935-1942 (Box 11)
  - West Coast exercise, 1937 (Box 11)
  - Wilcox bill, 1926-1937, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Military service record (201 file), 1920-1943, (5 folders) (Box 12)
  - Flight record, 1921-1943 (Box 12)
- Financial Papers, 1929-1942 (Box 13-15)
  Correspondence, bills, and receipts.
  - A-E, 1929-1942, (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - F-O, 1929-1942, (19 folders) (Box 14)
  - P-Z, 1929-1942, (15 folders) (Box 15)
- Speeches and Articles File, 1925-1942 (Box 16)
  Manuscript, typescript, and near-print copies of speeches and articles by Andrews and others.
  Arranged in approximate chronological order.
  - 1925-1942, (6 folders) (Box 16)
- Miscellany, 1929-1943 (Box 17)
  Social correspondence, calling cards, photographs, biographical material, and memorabilia.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Awards and decorations, 1935-1942 (Box 17)
  - Biographical material, 1940-1943, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Calling cards, 1941, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Christmas cards, 1942 (Box 17)
  - Invitations and programs, 1941-1942 (Box 17)
  - Memorandum receipts, 1929-1942 (Box 17)
  - Photographs, 1935-1941 (Box 17)
- Printed Matter, 1930-1943 (Box 18)
  Newspaper and magazine clippings, and miscellaneous printed matter.
  - Clippings, 1930-1943, (5 folders) (Box 18)
  - Miscellany, 1930-1941 (Box 18)
- Addition, 1930-1942 (Box 19)
  Personal correspondence and speeches.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Personal correspondence and speeches, 1930-1942, (13 folders) (Box 19)